<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>PabRod</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://pabrod.github.io/</id><updated>2018-04-23T12:24:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Welcome</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/welcome-en.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-23T12:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-23T12:24:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez</name></author><id>tag:pabrod.github.io,2018-04-23:/welcome-en.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Description of the motivations and topic of this blog&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Despite I have &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/site/pablorodriguezsanchez/"&gt;a personal webpage&lt;/a&gt; in Google Sites since some years ago, I got tired of updating it. The main reason is that it was an extremely manual task, that forced me to copypaste the same pieces of information in several places. The virtue of lazyness, when well understood, is the mother of programming and automation, so I started exploring other possibilities. In particular, I wanted something that could be well integrated with &lt;a href="https://yihui.name/knitr/"&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to the blog &lt;a href="https://rinzewind.org/blog-en/"&gt;Will do stuff for stuff&lt;/a&gt; I discovered &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, that allows to create websites from local files in a relatively easy way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two main problems I face at the early days of this new website are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Archiving&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some years working in science, I've produced a certain amount of materials that are now spread around at different webpages. Thanks to &lt;a href="https://yihui.name/knitr/"&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt;, I can keep this registry updated while only keeping updated a Spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For details, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/PabRod/academic-record"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Translating&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican gave me a nice surprise: it manages translations very well. This is specially relevant for me, because most of my work before my emigration to the Netherlands is written in Spanish. On the mid term, I hope to translate those materials whom I consider most relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What will I find here?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is easy: as in any other personal page, here you'll find anything the author considered worth being shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posts will be written in English, Spanish and/or, to a lesser extent, in Dutch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="about"></category></entry></feed>