<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>PabRod</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://pabrod.github.io/</id><updated>2018-06-10T12:27:50+02:00</updated><entry><title>Seminar announcement: A mathematician among biologists (Imperial College London)</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/seminar-imperial-en.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-10T12:27:50+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-10T12:27:50+02:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez</name></author><id>tag:pabrod.github.io,2018-06-10:/seminar-imperial-en.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Invasive species: a mathematician among biologists, 19 June 2018, Imperial College London&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Title&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invasive species: a mathematician among biologists&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a story about multidisciplinarity. It starts with a theoretical physicist being hired as a mathematician by a biology department. But what is the role of a mathematician in such a singular ecosystem? In this talk, we'll learn that the relation between biology and mathematics can be traced back to the XIII century. We'll also learn that the survival of plankton communities is strongly related with chaotic attractors, and how differential geometry had an unexpected role in a science communication problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wwwf.imperial.ac.uk/~mrasmuss/DynamIC/index.php"&gt;Department's website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spacetime coordinates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19 June 2018, 14:00-15:00 (local timezone)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huxley Building, South Kensington Campus. Room 130. Imperial College London.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2483.8125522417527!2d-0.1791236342303548!3d51.49830722963361!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x4876055c7df7c537%3A0x2541470e75df5fe0!2sHuxley+Building!5e0!3m2!1ses!2snl!4v1528627031939" width="600" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="math"></category><category term="biology"></category><category term="teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Course announcement: Introduction to PDEs</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/intro-to-pdes-en.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-06T13:13:30+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-06T13:13:30+02:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez</name></author><id>tag:pabrod.github.io,2018-06-06:/intro-to-pdes-en.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quick introduction to Partial Differential Equations, 7 June 2018, Wageningen University&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Quick introduction to Partial Differential Equations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday 7th, I'll give a crash course on partial differential equations at Wageningen University. Due to the diversity of backgrounds of the attendants, I'll try to focus in the key concepts, using graphical approaches as much as I can. Later on, we'll move forward to the numerical approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's the difference between partial and ordinary differential equations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vector calculus in a nutshell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classical PDEs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classical boundary conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hand-on examples with &lt;em&gt;Matlab&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please bring your laptop. The numerical examples will be solved using &lt;em&gt;Matlab's PDE Toolbox&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Materials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slides and some code examples are available at &lt;a href="https://github.com/PabRod/intro-to-pdes"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spacetime coordinates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7 June 2018, 13:30-16:30.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Room E.111, Lumen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="math"></category><category term="teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Embedding a Shiny app inside my blog</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/embed-shiny-en.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-05T15:54:09+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-05T15:54:09+02:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez</name></author><id>tag:pabrod.github.io,2018-05-05:/embed-shiny-en.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Embedding shiny apps inside an html page&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, I started experimenting with the computing language &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;. I have to confess that I don't feel fully comfortable with its syntax, which I find particularly difficult. But I forced myself to get used to it. Why? My main reasons were two: &lt;a href="https://yihui.name/knitr/"&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://shiny.rstudio.com"&gt;shiny&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knitr&lt;/strong&gt; is the perfect tool for literate computing. It allows the user to input a combination of code and markdown text providing a clean, human-readable document as output. Indeed, I'm using knitr for writing parts of this website (for example, the &lt;a href="https://pabrod.github.io/pages/sci-comm-en.html"&gt;dissemination section&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shiny&lt;/strong&gt; is great for making interactive apps, and publishing them as easy-to-use webpages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more (and certainly better) information... just google some tutorials. In this short entry, I only want to show an example of what shiny can do (and see how good it works with my new blog).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the following simulation I made some years ago to teach some basic ideas about statistical inference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://pabrod.shinyapps.io/shiny/"
        style="border: 2px solid black; width: 100%; height: 1000px;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps followed were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write the app itself. Of course, this is the difficult part.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish it. The easiest way is uploading it to &lt;a href="https://www.shinyapps.io"&gt;ShinyApps&lt;/a&gt;. The most popular &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; editor, &lt;a href="https://www.rstudio.com"&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;, can do this almost automatically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once this two steps are made, the insertion code I've used is as simple as:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;iframe src="https://pabrod.shinyapps.io/shiny/"
        style="border: 2px solid black; width: 100%; height: 1000px;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of simulation and interactive teaching. More apps will be published soon. Some of them can be previewed in &lt;a href="https://www.geogebra.org/u/pablorodriguez"&gt;GeoGebraTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="r"></category><category term="simulation"></category><category term="how-to"></category></entry><entry><title>There's a nerd in my elevator!</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/elevator-en.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-01T12:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-01T12:24:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez</name></author><id>tag:pabrod.github.io,2018-05-01:/elevator-en.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An elevator, a phone, ... and a nerd&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This text appeared first in &lt;a href="http://fuga.naukas.com/2018/02/06/un-empollon-en-mi-ascensor/"&gt;Naukas&lt;/a&gt;, where was originally written in Spanish.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I started a secondment at the Friedrich Schiller University, in Jena, Germany. Surprisingly, my office during the next months is located in the 18th floor of a skyscraper. The Jentower in particular:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Jentower" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/2018-01-30-16.34.25-360x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I'm not writing this to boast about the views of my new office. On the contrary, I'll destroy any possible idea of glamour related to work in a place like this. And I'll do it with a confession: I became the crazy guy who leaves his cell phone on the ground while he uses the elevator. Let me explain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A building of almost 150 meters high needs fast elevators. The ones in this building have a very powerful, scary acceleration. Then, I remembered that smartphones usually contain an accelerometer, so I tried to measure those accelerations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used an app called &lt;a href="https://sciencejournal.withgoogle.com"&gt;Google Science Journal&lt;/a&gt;, that allows registering data from all sensors available in the phone (accelerometers, light, magnetic field, ...) and export them in a format (.csv) quite easy to analyze on a computer. If you like getting your hands dirty, install it now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the figure below we can see the vertical acceleration profile during my trip to the 18th floor this morning, where we can clearly see the initial "kick" (seconds 9 to 14) and the braking (28 to 33)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="accel" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/acel1-580x391.png"&gt;
Vertical acceleration (excluding gravity)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accelerations of 1 m/s^2 sustained during 4 seconds! You can feel that in your stomach!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this data, we can explore a bit further. We can use a time series of the acceleration to compute speed and position. How? Maybe you remember from high school's physics that position, speed and acceleration are related through derivatives. More specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="diff" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/diff.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the previous recipe we can compute speed using the position, and then use speed to compute acceleration. Like in a production chain. Nevertheless, in our case we want to do the opposite process. Luckily, we can use indefinite integrals to "revert" our derivatives, and thus our whole "production chain".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="int" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/int.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by integrating the acceleration (to obtain the speed), and then integrating the speed (to obtain the position) we find results like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="results" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/all-580x564.png"&gt;
Acceleration, speed and position&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, using only a device that most of us carry everywhere and some elementary physical concepts we know that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our elevator runs up at 4 m/s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My office is 74 meter above the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a great time to be a nerd!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone is interested in exploring a bit deeper into the details (for instance: how to filter out the effects of gravity, how to integrate a time series, ... ) or even experiment with his or her own elevator, &lt;a href="https://github.com/PabRod/elevator-tool"&gt;here is a link&lt;/a&gt; to the code I've used.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="physics"></category><category term="python"></category></entry><entry><title>Welcome</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/welcome-en.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-23T12:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-23T12:24:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez</name></author><id>tag:pabrod.github.io,2018-04-23:/welcome-en.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Description of the motivations and topic of this blog&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Despite I have &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/site/pablorodriguezsanchez/"&gt;a personal webpage&lt;/a&gt; in Google Sites since some years ago, I got tired of updating it. The main reason is that it was an extremely manual task, that forced me to copypaste the same pieces of information in several places. The virtue of lazyness, when well understood, is the mother of programming and automation, so I started exploring other possibilities. In particular, I wanted something that could be well integrated with &lt;a href="https://yihui.name/knitr/"&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to the blog &lt;a href="https://rinzewind.org/blog-en/"&gt;Will do stuff for stuff&lt;/a&gt; I discovered &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, that allows to create websites from local files in a relatively easy way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two main problems I face at the early days of this new website are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Archiving&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some years working in science, I've produced a certain amount of materials that are now spread around at different webpages. Thanks to &lt;a href="https://yihui.name/knitr/"&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt;, I can keep this registry updated while only keeping updated a Spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For details, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/PabRod/academic-record"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Translating&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican gave me a nice surprise: it manages translations very well. This is specially relevant for me, because most of my work before my emigration to the Netherlands is written in Spanish. On the mid term, I hope to translate those materials whom I consider most relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What will I find here?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is easy: as in any other personal page, here you'll find anything the author considered worth being shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posts will be written in English, Spanish and/or, to a lesser extent, in Dutch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="about"></category></entry></feed>