<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>PabRod - python</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/feeds/tag-python.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://pabrod.github.io/</id><updated>2018-05-01T12:24:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>There's a nerd in my elevator!</title><link href="https://pabrod.github.io/elevator-en.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-01T12:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-01T12:24:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Rodríguez-Sánchez</name></author><id>tag:pabrod.github.io,2018-05-01:/elevator-en.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An elevator, a phone, ... and a nerd&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This text appeared first in &lt;a href="http://fuga.naukas.com/2018/02/06/un-empollon-en-mi-ascensor/"&gt;Naukas&lt;/a&gt;, where was originally written in Spanish.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I started a secondment at the Friedrich Schiller University, in Jena, Germany. Surprisingly, my office during the next months is located in the 18th floor of a skyscraper. The Jentower in particular:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Jentower" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/2018-01-30-16.34.25-360x640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I'm not writing this to boast about the views of my new office. On the contrary, I'll destroy any possible idea of glamour related to work in a place like this. And I'll do it with a confession: I became the crazy guy who leaves his cell phone on the ground while he uses the elevator. Let me explain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A building of almost 150 meters high needs fast elevators. The ones in this building have a very powerful, scary acceleration. Then, I remembered that smartphones usually contain an accelerometer, so I tried to measure those accelerations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used an app called &lt;a href="https://sciencejournal.withgoogle.com"&gt;Google Science Journal&lt;/a&gt;, that allows registering data from all sensors available in the phone (accelerometers, light, magnetic field, ...) and export them in a format (.csv) quite easy to analyze on a computer. If you like getting your hands dirty, install it now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the figure below we can see the vertical acceleration profile during my trip to the 18th floor this morning, where we can clearly see the initial "kick" (seconds 9 to 14) and the braking (28 to 33)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="accel" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/acel1-580x391.png"&gt;
Vertical acceleration (excluding gravity)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accelerations of 1 m/s^2 sustained during 4 seconds! You can feel that in your stomach!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this data, we can explore a bit further. We can use a time series of the acceleration to compute speed and position. How? Maybe you remember from high school's physics that position, speed and acceleration are related through derivatives. More specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="diff" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/diff.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the previous recipe we can compute speed using the position, and then use speed to compute acceleration. Like in a production chain. Nevertheless, in our case we want to do the opposite process. Luckily, we can use indefinite integrals to "revert" our derivatives, and thus our whole "production chain".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="int" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/int.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by integrating the acceleration (to obtain the speed), and then integrating the speed (to obtain the position) we find results like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="results" src="http://fuga.naukas.com/files/2018/02/all-580x564.png"&gt;
Acceleration, speed and position&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, using only a device that most of us carry everywhere and some elementary physical concepts we know that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our elevator runs up at 4 m/s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My office is 74 meter above the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a great time to be a nerd!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone is interested in exploring a bit deeper into the details (for instance: how to filter out the effects of gravity, how to integrate a time series, ... ) or even experiment with his or her own elevator, &lt;a href="https://github.com/PabRod/elevator-tool"&gt;here is a link&lt;/a&gt; to the code I've used.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="physics"></category><category term="python"></category></entry></feed>